<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-02-03T13:53:09-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/feed.xml</id>

  <title>Starburst developer blog</title>

  <subtitle>Your hub to all knowledge about Starburst products.</subtitle>

  
    <entry>
      <title>Increased CPU utilization in Trino</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-02-03-cpu-utilization.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Increased CPU utilization in Trino" />
      <published>2022-02-03T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/cpu-utilization</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-02-03-cpu-utilization.html">&lt;p&gt;While working on performance enhancements at Starburst, engineering focuses on
reducing the amount of time that a CPU has to work on a given query. This is
referred to as &lt;em&gt;CPU time&lt;/em&gt;. CPU time is a stable metric that reflects real
performance in the case of concurrent queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the CPU time for an individual query drops so can Trino’s ability to utilize
the CPUs fully; this can be due to scheduling as an example. The result is that
a reduction in CPU time does not always translate to a reduction in latency or
wall time. After a year of major performance enhancements we decided to focus
our efforts on increasing CPU utilization and reducing query wall time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cpu-utilization-enhancements&quot;&gt;CPU utilization enhancements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant change is that Trino’s
&lt;a href=&quot;../latest/admin/properties-query-management.html&quot;&gt;query.execution-policy&lt;/a&gt; now
defaults to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;phased&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;all-at-once&lt;/code&gt;. The all-at-once approach
scheduled all query stages in a single shot with the goal of simplicity and
reduced latency. The phased execution policy was later added as a configuration
option which would schedule only the stages of a query which can can make
progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, Karol Sobczak made the observation that the phased execution policy
can schedule stages that can create subsequent stages which can’t make progress.
That issue defeats the purpose of the phased execution policy. Fixing this logic
resulted in reduced latency, and the ability to set the phased execution policy
as default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-improvements&quot;&gt;Other improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other significant changes include adaptively setting &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;task.concurrency&lt;/code&gt; to the
number of physical cores on a node and increasing the default value of 
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hive.split-loader-concurrency&lt;/code&gt;. We have observed that hyper-threaded cores do
not translate to improved query performance. Increasing the split loader
concurrency helps the engine process partitions and small files more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benchmark-results&quot;&gt;Benchmark results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were impressed with a 20% reduction in wall time for TPC-H partitioned data,
and customers should be able to expect an average reduction of 13% in wall time
based on our internal benchmarking. We have seen improvements as high as 50%
for TPC-H query 12 on partitioned data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benchmark results were obtained by running the TPC-H and TPC-DS benchmarks
with one coordinator and six worker nodes. The data was queried by the Hive
connector with partitioned and unpartitioned data at 1TB scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/general/cpu-utilization-tpc-h-benchmark-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;TPC-H benchmark results for CPU utilization enhancements&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid &quot; description=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;px&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While TPC-H and TPC-DS are both decision support benchmarks TPC-H is said to be
more representative of ad hoc queries which tend to be simpler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/general/cpu-utilization-tpc-ds-benchmark-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;TPC-DS benchmark results for CPU utilization enhancements&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid &quot; description=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;px&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ready-for-you&quot;&gt;Ready for you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part about these changes mentioned above is that they do not require
any changes. They will be available out of the box in the upcoming LTS release.
Just remember that the software makes use of existing configurations so you
might need to unset &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;query.execution-policy&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;task.concurrency&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the even faster query processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Starburst Performance Team&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>While working on performance enhancements at Starburst, engineering focuses on reducing the amount of time that a CPU has to work on a given query. This is referred to as CPU time. CPU time is a stable metric that reflects real performance in the case of concurrent queries. As the CPU time for an individual query drops so can Trino’s ability to utilize the CPUs fully; this can be due to scheduling as an example. The result is that a reduction in CPU time does not always translate to a reduction in latency or wall time. After a year of major performance enhancements we decided to focus our efforts on increasing CPU utilization and reducing query wall time.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Starburst Enterprise 369-e STS</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-02-01-sep-369-e.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starburst Enterprise 369-e STS" />
      <published>2022-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/sep-369-e</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-02-01-sep-369-e.html">&lt;p&gt;We are not resting, on the contrary. Today we are bringing you another STS
release packed with great new features to try and use. And we are solidifying
everything for the upcoming LTS release as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trino&quot;&gt;Trino&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the 369-e STS release first though. It is based on Trino 369, which
added a couple of amazing new features, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experimental support for task-level retries.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for groups in OAuth2 claims.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Column comments in ClickHouse connector.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write Bloom filters in ORC files.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Procedure for optimizing Iceberg tables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release also &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/trinodb/trino/issues/10710&quot;&gt;fixes an S3/Parquet file data
issue&lt;/a&gt; for users of &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html&quot;&gt;367-e&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022-01-18-sep-368-e.html&quot;&gt;368-e&lt;/a&gt;, who used AWS S3 with streaming enabled with the Hive, Iceberg, or Delta
Lake connectors, so make sure you update if this applies to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in the upcoming support for query and task-level retries,
and our work towards even better support for ETL and batch operations, you can
learn more in &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/episodes/32.html&quot;&gt;episode 32 of the Trino Community Broadcast about Project
Tardigrade&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starburst-enterprise&quot;&gt;Starburst Enterprise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/release/release-369-e.html&quot;&gt;Starburst Enterprise 369-e STS release
notes&lt;/a&gt; itself, the biggest standout is the
preview of our &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/security/biac-overview.html&quot;&gt;new built-in access
control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users of Starburst Galaxy are already used to a &lt;a href=&quot;../starburst-galaxy/security/index.html&quot;&gt;powerful, integrated access
control system&lt;/a&gt;. And of course, we are
not leaving Starburst Enterprise users behind. In fact, the new built-in
access control is even more powerful, and includes features such as table level
access control. Try it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/general/sep-biac.png&quot; alt=&quot;Starburst Enterprise built-in access control&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid img-screenshot&quot; description=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;px&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release also includes numerous improvements for the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/connector/starburst-delta-lake.html&quot;&gt;Starburst Delta Lake
connector&lt;/a&gt; and Kerberos
authentication support for the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/connector/starburst-memsql.html&quot;&gt;SingleStore
connector&lt;/a&gt;. And our connector pages
include colorful logos now as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-up&quot;&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you enjoy testing this new release. See you next time on the LTS
announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Matt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>We are not resting, on the contrary. Today we are bringing you another STS release packed with great new features to try and use. And we are solidifying everything for the upcoming LTS release as well.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Starburst Enterprise 368-e STS</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-01-18-sep-368-e.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starburst Enterprise 368-e STS" />
      <published>2022-01-18T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/sep-368-e</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-01-18-sep-368-e.html">&lt;p&gt;Today we are starting the year 2022 off with a great new release of
Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP). Believe us, you do want to try out the refreshed
Starburst Enterprise web UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following up on the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html&quot;&gt;367-e STS release from the end of 2021&lt;/a&gt;, we have another set of changes ready for you. Today we
are releasing &lt;a href=&quot;../368-e/index.html&quot;&gt;Starburst Enterprise 368-e
STS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual this release is based on Trino, and Martin Traverso
announced the following major improvements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve performance of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DECIMAL&lt;/code&gt; type&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;File-based access control for Apache Iceberg connector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TIME&lt;/code&gt; type in SingleStore connector&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;BINARY&lt;/code&gt; type in Apache Phoenix connector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Starburst Enterprise side we &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/release/release-368-e.html&quot;&gt;added a few more
improvements&lt;/a&gt;. The biggest change is our
rebranded and refreshed &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/overview/sep-ui.html&quot;&gt;Starburst Enterprise web
UI&lt;/a&gt;. Over the last few releases we have added
more features and polished everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Starburst Enterprise web UI offers access to the query editor, data
products, query history, cluster information, usage metrics and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/general/sep-ui-cluster-overview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Starburst Enterprise web UI&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid img-screenshot&quot; description=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;px&quot; style=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a data consumer you can write and test your queries right in the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/client/query-editor.html&quot;&gt;query
editor&lt;/a&gt; without the needs to configure
another tool. And once the query runs you can analyze its processing metrics and
more information in the query details. As a data engineer, you can quickly and
easily test that new catalog you just added, and confirm access to the nested
schemas and tables works as expected. And as a platform administrator you can
check cluster status, query history, and usage metrics to figure out when it is
time to add another worker to that busy cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just some of the use cases you can play around with in the user
interface. We definitely want you to check it out. Did we miss something? Is
something not working? Contact us so we can get it improved in time for the
upcoming LTS release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Matt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update, 2022-01-27:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 368-e and 367-e, writing to Hive, Iceberg, or Delta tables on S3 or
S3-compatible storage with a streaming upload enabled can write corrupted data
files without reporting an error back to the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 368-e streaming uploads are enabled by default. As a results users may
encounter this without taking any action to enable streaming in their
configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 367-e streaming upload are disabled by default. However it is a common
practice to enable streaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fix we recommend to set &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hive.s3.streaming.enabled=false&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;trino.s3.streaming.enabled=false&lt;/code&gt; in all catalog property files using S3 with
the Hive, Iceberg or Delta Lake connector.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>Today we are starting the year 2022 off with a great new release of Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP). Believe us, you do want to try out the refreshed Starburst Enterprise web UI.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>A Trino and dbt community success story</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-01-03-dbt-trino.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Trino and dbt community success story" />
      <published>2022-01-03T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/dbt-trino</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-01-03-dbt-trino.html">&lt;p&gt;The community around the open source project Trino is at the heart
of Starburst. The creators and many maintainers are on our teams. Our
products, Starburst Enterprise and Starburst Galaxy are based on
Trino. And today, I tell you a story that shows how it takes a many
people across the globe to provide all the great features of Trino
to our community of users and fellow contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start our story in Europe. In Vienna, Austria to be precise. Marius got
interested into Trino there and started to learn more about it by
trying it out. It did not take long and he showed up on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/community.html&quot;&gt;community
channels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marius bumped into Brian and Manfred on the slack channels, and after a few
chats online and in video calls he joined us as guest in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/episodes/20.html&quot;&gt;Trino Community
Broadcast episode 20&lt;/a&gt;. We talked about his
experience as beginner, and his advances to documentation and code contributor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/episodes/21.html&quot;&gt;episode 21&lt;/a&gt;, Brian and Manfred learned
more about dbt and Trino. We also learned that back then we still
had to use the legacy Presto support. And the next day we had a proof of concept
implementation for Trino dbt support in our hands. Marius was at it
again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this implementation ready to go, Starburst and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.getdbt.com/&quot;&gt;dbt
labs&lt;/a&gt; started to collaborate towards a fully supported
release. And a few months later the benefits showed up for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian and Manfred recorded &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/episodes/30.html&quot;&gt;episode 30 of the Trino Community
Broadcast&lt;/a&gt; about real world usage of dbt at
Trino at Talkdesk in November. We were also joined by our dbt
champion at Starburst, Przemek, and learned about his work to make the
integration fully tested and feature rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marius and Przemek worked with Starburst teams in the USA and Poland to
get the integration further improved. This resulted in a fully tested and
supported release 1.0.0 of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/starburstdata/dbt-trino&quot;&gt;dbt-trino&lt;/a&gt; in December 2021. And of
course, this integration is open source and available for you all to test and
use. Watch the episodes and get started with &lt;a href=&quot;../data-consumer/clients/dbt.html&quot;&gt;our dbt client
documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course our thanks go out to all the other helpers on the way, including
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/leniartek&quot;&gt;Piotr&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/yuanamychen/&quot;&gt;Amy&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/victorcouste&quot;&gt;Victor&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jecabeda&quot;&gt;José&lt;/a&gt;. And if you got &lt;a href=&quot;../data-consumer/clients/index.html&quot;&gt;another client
integration&lt;/a&gt;, or other feature to test or
contribute, don’t hesitate to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred, Brian, and Marius&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>The community around the open source project Trino is at the heart of Starburst. The creators and many maintainers are on our teams. Our products, Starburst Enterprise and Starburst Galaxy are based on Trino. And today, I tell you a story that shows how it takes a many people across the globe to provide all the great features of Trino to our community of users and fellow contributors.</summary>

      
      
        <media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://docs.starburst.io/assets/img/logo/dbt.svg" />
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>When it comes to security...</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-31-security.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When it comes to security..." />
      <published>2021-12-31T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/security</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-31-security.html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve got you covered. The recent &lt;a href=&quot;../security/log4shell.html&quot;&gt;log4shell issue&lt;/a&gt;
is the latest noise in the information security world. And as is often the case
with these issues, if you have your software development and information
security processes under control, there is more hype than reality around the
threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see from our swift responses to the log4shell issue in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/blog/2021/12/13/log4shell-does-not-affect-trino.html&quot;&gt;Trino
community&lt;/a&gt;,
and our own releases of 
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html&quot;&gt;Starburst Enterprise LTS backports&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html&quot;&gt;a new STS release&lt;/a&gt; that we have years
of experience with security in our teams. We were essentially not affected, but
took the opportunity to trim our binaries and tighten our processes yet again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to give you and idea, what we do to ensure your data secure we added a new
security section. It now details many of our processes and procedures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//corporate.html&quot;&gt;Corporate information security policies and procedures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//development.html&quot;&gt;Software development and security practices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//starburst-enterprise.html&quot;&gt;Security and Starburst Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//starburst-galaxy.html&quot;&gt;Security and Starburst Galaxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security/contact.html&quot;&gt;Contact us&lt;/a&gt; to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Keavy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>We’ve got you covered. The recent log4shell issue is the latest noise in the information security world. And as is often the case with these issues, if you have your software development and information security processes under control, there is more hype than reality around the threats.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Starburst Enterprise 367-e STS</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starburst Enterprise 367-e STS" />
      <published>2021-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/sep-367-e</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html">&lt;p&gt;Promise! This is the last Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) release of the year 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html&quot;&gt;recent LTS backport release train&lt;/a&gt; in your hands, we just had to cut a release of a
new STS to finish up the work around &lt;a href=&quot;../security/log4shell.html&quot;&gt;log4shell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the release includes more than just upgrades and removal of unused
log4j binaries. In fact, if you look at the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/release/release-367-e.html&quot;&gt;367-e release
notes&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/release/release-365-e.html&quot;&gt;365-e release
notes&lt;/a&gt; you see a number of new features
and changes that are definitely worth trying out. Specifically our &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/insights.html&quot;&gt;new default
web interface for SEP&lt;/a&gt; includes numerous
things to play with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplified configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add live query plan display.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add new &lt;em&gt;Data products&lt;/em&gt; as experimental feature.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased scope of telemetry data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New filters in query history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you are still running the &lt;a href=&quot;../364-e/index.html&quot;&gt;364-e LTS release&lt;/a&gt; in
productions, I strongly suggest you play with the new 367-e release. And of
course, make sure to let us know of any feedback to allow us to improve
SEP even more for the next releases. There is plenty coming
in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Matt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update, 2022-01-27:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 368-e and 367-e, writing to Hive, Iceberg, or Delta tables on S3 or
S3-compatible storage with a streaming upload enabled can write corrupted data
files without reporting an error back to the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 368-e streaming uploads are enabled by default. As a results users may
encounter this without taking any action to enable streaming in their
configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 367-e streaming upload are disabled by default. However it is a common
practice to enable streaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fix we recommend to set &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hive.s3.streaming.enabled=false&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;trino.s3.streaming.enabled=false&lt;/code&gt; in all catalog property files using S3 with
the Hive, Iceberg or Delta Lake connector.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>Promise! This is the last Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) release of the year 2021.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>December 2021 LTS backport releases</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="December 2021 LTS backport releases" />
      <published>2021-12-17T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/lts-backports</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html">&lt;p&gt;We did it again! A bunch of new backport releases for our
Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) LTS users are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following are the new available versions linking to the relevant release notes
entries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/350-e/release/release-350-e.html&quot;&gt;350-e.18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/356-e/release/release-356-e.html&quot;&gt;356-e.11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/360-e/release/release-360-e.html&quot;&gt;360-e.8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/364-e/release/release-364-e.html&quot;&gt;364-e.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the related Helm charts and other resources are all available as part
of the update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the usual backports for correctness issues, this release train had a
focus point around the log4shell vulnerabilities. Despite the fact that
Trino and Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/blog/2021/12/13/log4shell-does-not-affect-trino.html&quot;&gt;are not
affected&lt;/a&gt;,
we decided to eliminate any potential risk of exposure. Now log4j binaries are
either gone completely or updated to unaffected version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the details can be found in the release notes and the dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;../security/log4shell.html&quot;&gt;security
advisory for log4shell&lt;/a&gt; in our brand new &lt;a href=&quot;../security/index.html&quot;&gt;security
section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Matt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>We did it again! A bunch of new backport releases for our Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) LTS users are available.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
