<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-01-04T15:09:55-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/feed.xml</id>

  <title>Starburst tech blog</title>

  <subtitle>Your hub to all knowledge about Starburst products.</subtitle>

  
    <entry>
      <title>A Trino and dbt community success story</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-01-03-dbt-trino.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Trino and dbt community success story" />
      <published>2022-01-03T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/dbt-trino</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2022-01-03-dbt-trino.html">&lt;p&gt;The community around the open source project Trino is at the heart
of Starburst. The creators and many maintainers are on our teams. Our
products, Starburst Enterprise and Starburst Galaxy are based on
Trino. And today, I tell you a story that shows how it takes a many
people across the globe to provide all the great features of Trino
to our community of users and fellow contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start our story in Europe. In Vienna, Austria to be precise. Marius got
interested into Trino there and started to learn more about it by
trying it out. It did not take long and he showed up on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/community.html&quot;&gt;community
channels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marius bumped into Brian and Manfred on the slack channels, and after a few
chats online and in video calls he joined us as guest in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/episodes/20.html&quot;&gt;Trino Community
Broadcast episode 20&lt;/a&gt;. We talked about his
experience as beginner, and his advances to documentation and code contributor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/episodes/21.html&quot;&gt;episode 21&lt;/a&gt;, Brian and Manfred learned
more about dbt and Trino. We also learned that back then we still
had to use the legacy Presto support. And the next day we had a proof of concept
implementation for Trino dbt support in our hands. Marius was at it
again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this implementation ready to go, Starburst and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.getdbt.com/&quot;&gt;dbt
labs&lt;/a&gt; started to collaborate towards a fully supported
release. And a few months later the benefits showed up for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian and Manfred recorded &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/episodes/30.html&quot;&gt;episode 30 of the Trino Community
Broadcast&lt;/a&gt; about real world usage of dbt at
Trino at Talkdesk in November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marius worked with Starburst teams in the USA and Poland to get the
integration further improved. This resulted in a fully tested and supported
release 1.0.0 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/starburstdata/dbt-trino&quot;&gt;dbt-trino&lt;/a&gt; in
December 2021. And of course, this integration is open source and available for
you all to test and use. Watch the episodes and get started with &lt;a href=&quot;../data-consumer/clients/dbt.html&quot;&gt;our dbt client
documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course our thanks go out to all the other helpers on the way, including Alex,
Piotr, Przemysław, Amy, Victor, and José. And if you got &lt;a href=&quot;../data-consumer/clients/index.html&quot;&gt;another client
integration&lt;/a&gt;, or other feature to test or
contribute, don’t hesitate to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred, Brian, and Marius&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>The community around the open source project Trino is at the heart of Starburst. The creators and many maintainers are on our teams. Our products, Starburst Enterprise and Starburst Galaxy are based on Trino. And today, I tell you a story that shows how it takes a many people across the globe to provide all the great features of Trino to our community of users and fellow contributors.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>When it comes to security, ...</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-31-security.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When it comes to security, ..." />
      <published>2021-12-31T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/security</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-31-security.html">&lt;p&gt;we got you. The recent &lt;a href=&quot;../security/log4shell.html&quot;&gt;log4shell issue&lt;/a&gt; is the
latest noise in the information security world. And as is often the case with
these issues, if you have your software development and information security
processes under control, there is more hype than reality around the threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see from our swift responses to the log4shell issue in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/blog/2021/12/13/log4shell-does-not-affect-trino.html&quot;&gt;Trino
community&lt;/a&gt;,
and our own releases of 
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html&quot;&gt;Starburst Enterprise LTS backports&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html&quot;&gt;a new STS release&lt;/a&gt; that we have years
of experience with security in our teams. We were essentially not affected, but
took the opportunity to trim our binaries and tighten our processes yet again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to give you and idea, what we do to ensure your data secure we added a new
security section. It now details many of our processes and procedures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//corporate.html&quot;&gt;Corporate information security policies and procedures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//development.html&quot;&gt;Software development and security practices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//starburst-enterprise.html&quot;&gt;Security and Starburst Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security//starburst-galaxy.html&quot;&gt;Security and Starburst Galaxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../security/contact.html&quot;&gt;Contact us&lt;/a&gt; to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Keavy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>we got you. The recent log4shell issue is the latest noise in the information security world. And as is often the case with these issues, if you have your software development and information security processes under control, there is more hype than reality around the threats.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Starburst Enterprise 367-e STS</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starburst Enterprise 367-e STS" />
      <published>2021-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/sep-367-e</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-29-sep-367-e.html">&lt;p&gt;Promise! This is the last Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) release of the year 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html&quot;&gt;recent LTS backport release train&lt;/a&gt; in your hands, we just had to cut a release of a
new STS to finish up the work around &lt;a href=&quot;../security/log4shell.html&quot;&gt;log4shell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the release includes more than just upgrades and removal of unused
log4j binaries. In fact, if you look at the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/release/release-367-e.html&quot;&gt;367-e release
notes&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/release/release-365-e.html&quot;&gt;365-e release
notes&lt;/a&gt; you see a number of new features
and changes that are definitely worth trying out. Specifically our &lt;a href=&quot;../latest/insights.html&quot;&gt;new default
web interface for SEP&lt;/a&gt; includes numerous
things to play with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplified configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add live query plan display.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add new &lt;em&gt;Data products&lt;/em&gt; as experimental feature.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased scope of telemetry data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New filters in query history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you are still running the &lt;a href=&quot;../364-e/index.html&quot;&gt;364-e LTS release&lt;/a&gt; in
productions, I strongly suggest you play with the new 367-e release. And of
course, make sure to let us know of any feedback to allow us to improve
SEP even more for the next releases. There is plenty coming
in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Matt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>Promise! This is the last Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) release of the year 2021.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>December 2021 LTS backport releases</title>
      <link href="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="December 2021 LTS backport releases" />
      <published>2021-12-17T00:00:00-06:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
      <id>https://docs.starburst.io/blog/lts-backports</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://docs.starburst.io/blog/2021-12-17-lts-backports.html">&lt;p&gt;We did it again! A bunch of new backport releases for our
Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) LTS users are available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following are the new available versions linking to the relevant release notes
entries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/350-e/release/release-350-e.html&quot;&gt;350-e.18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/356-e/release/release-356-e.html&quot;&gt;356-e.11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/360-e/release/release-360-e.html&quot;&gt;360-e.8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/364-e/release/release-364-e.html&quot;&gt;364-e.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the related Helm charts and other resources are all available as part
of the update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the usual backports for correctness issues, this release train had a
focus point around the log4shell vulnerabilities. Despite the fact that
Trino and Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) &lt;a href=&quot;https://trino.io/blog/2021/12/13/log4shell-does-not-affect-trino.html&quot;&gt;are not
affected&lt;/a&gt;,
we decided to eliminate any potential risk of exposure. Now log4j binaries are
either gone completely or updated to unaffected version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the details can be found in the release notes and the dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;../security/log4shell.html&quot;&gt;security
advisory for log4shell&lt;/a&gt; in our brand new &lt;a href=&quot;../security/index.html&quot;&gt;security
section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manfred and Matt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      <summary>We did it again! A bunch of new backport releases for our Starburst Enterprise platform (SEP) LTS users are available.</summary>

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
